Okay I'll start that one. Okay. Okay starting. Okay great I think
we're going.
Okay so we are on דף מ''ב Daf Mem Beis and
we're picking up with the first איתיבי Itibi on the page
which is about 10 lines down. So we're going back to the
conversation that we started yesterday or yeah yesterday of what
happens with idols that break on their own right? Like you stumble
upon an idol that's like just broken on its own of its
own accord? And we have a מחלוקת Machlokes between רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says those
are אסור Assur right? You need to actually have a non-Jew break
the idol
himself as a way of like saying this idol is no longer
no longer holds importance to me and that's what makes it ביטול
Bittul but and so if it just breaks on its own it's
still אסור Assur and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no it's מותר
Muttar because because the non-Jew will say well look if the idol
just couldn't protect itself like it just broke on its own then
it must not be a very good idol and he's going to
like in his mind ביטול Bittul it and say that it's no
longer an idol for him or holds any power for him. Okay
so we're going to go through a numerous
challenges to the opinion of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. We're going to
have רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan challenging ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and each
one ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is going to kind of knock back.
And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to do this by the
kind of the method he's going to use is he's going to
say there's another case where we say that the idol is
still אסור Assur and so and you know if that case is
still אסור Assur why wouldn't you know if it's true ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish that an idol that breaks on its own is מותר
Muttar why wouldn't this other case also be מותר? Muttar? It seems
like it should be a similar case and it should also be
מותר Muttar and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is going to have an
answer or the גמרא Gemara is going to have an answer in
the name of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish each time.
Okay. איתיבי Itibi מצא תבנית יד תבנית רגל הרי אלו אסורין. Matza
Tavnit Yad, Tavnit Regel, Harei Elu Assurin. So this is we already
kind of had this discussion so you guys should recognize it right?
So thanks to Dan's drawing up here you have well let's let's
pause on the drawing first. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying look
you find a piece of a statue that's just like a foot
or just a hand just a hand or just a foot these
are אסור Assur right? Even these little pieces of statue מפני שכיוצא
בהן נעבד Mipnei Shekeyotzei Bahen Na'avad because they're like something that's been
worshipped. What? מ''ב. Mem Beis.
Oh where in the גמרא? Gemara? Yeah. מ''ב Mem Beis about 10
lines down the first
איתיבי. Itibi. It's in the middle of the תוספות Tosafos that starts
with מפני Mipnei that's like lined up with that. Right across from
the מ''א מ''ב Mem Aleph Mem Beis if that's what you have.
Or it's lined up with the נפל לבור אלא אם הטיל לכם
מנפל. Nafal-l-Bur Ela Im Hetil-l-Kam Mi-nafal. No go down go down. אם
רוח הפילו אם. Im Ruach Hapilu Im. Farther down.
Keep on going. When it gets back to מצא תבנית יד תבנית
רגל. Matza Tavnit Yad Tavnit Regel. Glory you want to point it
out for him? I'm not sure. מצא תבנית Matza Tavnit Yes yes
yes. We're on מ''ב Mem Beis עמוד א'. Amud Aleph. We just
read that part. Yeah so that's where we are. Okay. Great. I
like the א' Aleph that helps. There you go. Okay we're good?
Okay so you find these pieces of statues they're אסור Assur because
they're like something that's been worshipped right? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says אמאי? Amai? הא שברים נינהו. Ha Shevarim Ninhu. So he's saying
according to you ריש לקיש Reish Lakish why would this be?
They're pieces right? So just
like a pretty good question right? A statue that breaks on its
own is מותר Muttar so why wouldn't these pieces of statues which
maybe broke on their own maybe someone else broke
them why wouldn't those be מותר Muttar also? Sorry. So then we're
going to have the same answer that we had yesterday which is
הא תרגמה שמואל בעומדין על בסיסן. Ha Targema Shmuel Be'omdin Al Basisam.
So שמואל Shmuel interprets the משנה Mishnah in the way to be
that these pieces of hand or foot are actually on a pedestal.
So if you look here Dan did a very good job of
showing so it looks like it's not a piece of a broken
statue after all it's actually like a statue that is just a
foot like that was how it was meant to be originally. See
but that's so you know for sure it's just meant to be
a foot? Well
look so the better answer would be there's no broken anything here
it's like clearly a whole statue. I don't know that's not what
שמואל Shmuel says but it seems like that's the... Right because I
get from that like let's say the top the whole rest of
it was broken but it still happens to be on the pedestal
you know what I mean? Right right right I don't think that's
what he's talking about I think he's saying look you find a
piece of you find a statue that's clearly his way of saying
it is that it's on a pedestal but he's saying it's clearly
just the foot was the entirety of the idol in the beginning
to begin with. Because apparently feet were a thing that they worshipped.
Feet and hands I guess I don't yeah I mean you could
imagine...
Like the hand particularly, right, like a god that's like giving you
something, right, so maybe that feels powerful, I don't know. Okay,
so Resh Lakish beats, you know, kind of beats that challenge back
by saying: No, no, no, those are whole whole idols to begin
with, they're not pieces. איתיבי itivei. *Eitivei*, so Rabbi Yochanan tries again.
עובד כוכבים oved kochavim, מבטל mevattel עבודת כוכבים שלו ושל חבירו *Oved
kochavim mivatel avodat kochavim shelo veshel chaveiro*. So a non-Jew can be
מבטל mevattel, *mivatel* the idol, his own idol or a friend's idol,
like any non-Jew's idol basically. וישראל אינו מבטל mevattel, עבודת כוכבים של
עובד כוכבים *VeYisrael eino mivatel avodat kochavim shel oved kochavim*. But a
non-Jew cannot... a Jew, thank you, cannot come in
and מבטל mevattel, *mivatel* the idol
of a non-Jew, right, in any way, right? אמאי amai, *Amai*? So
Rabbi Yochanan is saying: Resh Lakish, why would this be? If an
idol that breaks on its own
is מותר mutar, *mutar*, why wouldn't an idol that a Jew breaks
be מותר mutar, *mutar*? It seems like that should be even more
מותר mutar? *mutar*, right? תהוי בעבודת כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה *Tehavi b'avodat kochavim
shenishbeira me'aleha*, right, so it should be as good as one that
breaks on its own. אמר אביי amar Abaye, שבפחסה *Amar Abaye shepichasa*.
So actually this isn't a... we're not talking about a broken idol,
we're talking about an idol that the Jew bent or Rashi says
he like took a hammer to it and like flattened it out,
he like ruined the shape of it, right? וכי פחסה מאי הוי
*Vekipichasa mai havei*? So why should it matter? Resh Lakish says: It's
bent, it's not broken, but why does that matter? It still seems
to be ruined, right? והתנן פחסה אף על פי שלא חסרה בטלה
*Vehatnan pichasa af al pi shelo chasra batla*. Right, we even have
a משנה Mishna. *mishna* that says that if it's bent, even if
it doesn't like technically break, it's still a good way... it's a
successful way of מבטל mevattel *mivatel*-ing the idol, right? So it seems
like
the challenge to Resh Lakish still stands, right? So Resh Lakish is
going to try again. הני מילי דפחסה עובד כוכבים *Hani mili depichasa
oved kochavim*. So that is talking about when you say that it
works to bend it and that successfully בטלה *batla*-s it, that is
when a non-Jew does that. אבל פחסה ישראל Yisrael. לא בטלה *Aval
pichasa Yisrael lo batla*. But it doesn't work when a Jew does
that. Why not? Good question. Let's see what Rashi says. אבל פחסה
ישראל דלא דמי לעבודת כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה *Aval pichasa Yisrael d'lo dami
l'avodat kochavim shenishbeira me'aleha*. So it doesn't seem like... well he's saying
it is, to me it seems exactly like that. Because he's saying
פחסה *pichasa* ממש *mamash*. אישתא לא מצי מציל לנפשיה *Ishta lo matzi
matzil lenafsheih*, that's what we had before, like the... it can't save
itself, how is it going to save me? Right. Right, so here
it's saying: Well what do you mean it couldn't save itself? The
Jew came in and smashed it. But it didn't save itself. Right,
but I think it's maybe we're thinking like the non-Jew has enough
like cognizance of like the way physical things work in the world
that if someone's going to come along and smash it... והא Veha,
הכא לא אמרינן עובד כוכבים בטילתה עבודת כוכבים אפחסה *Veha hecha lo
amrina oved kochavim batltah avodat kochavim apichasa*. It's like, eh, I don't
care so much if it's, you know, flattened out and I don't
know. I would think he would care. Right, but you can understand
the difference between like there's an idol on the shelf over there
and it just spontaneously falls over and breaks. You're like, whoa, that
seems like something's going on in the, you know, spiritual world that
this idol like is just knocked over and like maybe the god
doesn't, you know, like me anymore, maybe whatever, right? Versus a person
comes along and smashes it and you're like well you just smashed
my idol. That doesn't seem as like god-influenced I feel like maybe,
right?
Anyway. So let's see. It's okay that you don't like it Michael,
because Resh Lakish has another option, right? He says or let's say
this. And this one let's pay attention to this answer because this
answer is going to come up for the rest of this עמוד
amud. *amud*. It's going to keep being Resh Lakish's answer. ורבה אמר
Amar לעולם כי פחסה ישראל נמי בטלה *Verabba amar le'olam ki pichasa
Yisrael nami batla*. So actually it actually does work Michael when a
Jew comes along and does this, it does בטלה *batla* the idol
theoretically. אלא *Ella* גזירה gezeirah *gezeira*... the rabbis made a גזירה gezeirah
*gezeira*... דילמא *dilma* מגבה לה והדר מבטלה *magbah lah vehadar mivattelah*. So
maybe the Jew is going to want to מבטל m'vatel. *mivatel* it
and in order to to hammer it and bend it out of
shape, he's going to come over and pick it up and then
try to מבטל m'vatel *mivatel* it. והויא עבודת כוכבים ביד ישראל וכל
עבודת כוכבים ביד ישראל אינה בטלה לעולם *Vehavyei avodat kochavim b'yad Yisrael
vechol avodat kochavim b'yad Yisrael einah betelah le'olam*. But by picking it
up we know that something that's like הפקר *hefker* if a Jew
comes along and picks it up, he takes ownership of it and...
so in order to bend it out of shape the Jew's going
to pick it up, take ownership of it, and then we know
that that then he's going to own it and an idol that
a Jew owns can't ever be בטלה *batla* ever, and so then
we're then we're stuck with an idol that now holds power forever,
we can't actually מבטל m'vatel *mivatel* it ever. So the Rabbis made
a גזירה gezeirah so that a Jew wouldn't come along and pick
it up in order to bend it out of shape, that if
a Jew does that, it's not מבטל mevatel it. Does that make
sense? Good.
Can you get benefit, like if it's made out of metal, to
use the metal for something? I want to... Once it's מבטל, mevatel
you're saying? Yeah. I think so, I think that's the whole point
is, like, once it's מבטל, then you can... you'll see some examples
later on, that I think that I think, yeah, once it's מבטל,
you can use it for something else, but while it's still an
idol, you can't get benefit from it. But we can ask Rabbi
Linder tomorrow to double check. Okay, איתיבי. itivei. So we're going to
try again for Rabbi Yochanan, right? איתיבי. itivei, אקום שהביא אבנים מן
המרקוליס. akum sheheivi avanim min ha-markolis.
So a non-Jew who brings stones from a מרקוליס, markolis, which is
like a pile of... I think Rashi tells us a pile of
stones that's to the god of Mercury, and people come by and
throw more stones at it, and that's the way of worshipping it.
So you take stones from this pile, right, which is clearly a
pile dedicated to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right? That's the way the
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is done is by putting stones in this
pile. וחיפה בהן דרכים ותרטיאות, v'chippa bahen drachim v'tarti'ot,
and you pave with them roads or theaters, תרטיאות, tarti'ot, or we
have another גרסא girsa that says... Is that תיאטראות, tiatrot, theaters? Yeah,
yeah, exactly. Or we have another גרסא girsa that says סרטיאות, sarti'ot,
which would be highways, which might make more sense.
מותרות, mutarot, right? So those highways, you can get benefit from those
highways and roads, you can drive on them, it's מותר, mutar, right?
וישראל שהביא אבנים מן המרקוליס וחיפה בהן דרכים ותרטיאות, v'Yisrael sheheivi avanim
min ha-markolis v'chippa bahen drachim v'tarti'ot,
but if a Jew does the same thing, אסורות. asurot. So those
are אסור. assur. It doesn't work for the Jew to take the
stones and build something else from them to מבטל them. They still
hold the power of עבודה זרה avodah zarah and therefore those roads
and theaters would be אסור. assur. אמאי, Amai, says Rabbi Yochanan, if
according to you, Reish Lakish, if an idol breaks on its own
why wouldn't this and that's מותר, mutar then why wouldn't this also
be מותר? mutar. תהא כעבודת כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה. tehavi k'avodat kochavim shenishtabra
me'eleha.
It should be the same thing. הכא נמי כדרבה. hacha nami k'derabba.
So Reish Lakish's answer is this is also like Rabba's opinion that
says
that we made a גזירה gezeirah so that Jews wouldn't pick them
up
and then take ownership of them, right? So we're theoretically it would
work for a Jew, but we're saying it doesn't, right? Okay. Rabbi
Yochanan, איתיבי, Eitivei, right?
We're
going to try again. עובד כוכבים ששפה עבודת כוכבים לצרכו היא ושיפוחיה
מותרין. oved kochavim sheshippa avodat kochavim l'tzarcho hi ushipuheiha mutarin.
So a non-Jew comes along and takes his idol and he's shaving
it down, right? I guess theoretically it would be
like upkeep of the idol. It gets like dirty on the outside
maybe or something like that. For some reason he's shaving it down.
And it says לצרכו, l'tzarcho, it's for the sake of the idol,
right? It's something to improve the idol. Then the idol, היא ושיפוחיה,
hi ushipuheiha, and the shavings themselves are מותרין, mutarin, all of it.
Wait, wait, but היא hi is the... Oh, sorry, לצרכו, l'tzarcho, I'm
sorry, you're right. לצרכו l'tzarcho is for the sake of the עובד
כוכבים, right? For the non-Jew, and we're going to get to that
other case later. Right, in this case he's shaving it down because
he like wants the shavings or something like that, right? So there
we take that as a sign that he clearly does not respect
this idol very much because he's willing to shave it down in
order to like get shavings from it. But it's still in existence,
just less of it. Like instead of it... I don't think it's
that it's less of it. I don't think it's about it being
broken. I think it's about the mindset of the non-Jew. No, no,
but I'm saying you can still, like you still look at it
and you're like, oh yeah, this is totally an idol of whatever
it is. Sure, yeah, it's like faces just total scraped off or
it's, you know. I mean, I think you could see that it's
shaved, so right. But the point is that the non-Jew wouldn't do
that unless he... He's doing it to get the shavings. He's doing
it to get the shavings. So the whole point is what's the
use you could make of the shavings. Well both, this says היא
ושיפוחיה. hi ushipuheiha. It says the idol and the shavings, right? So
we're saying both are מותר, mutar right? Which is pretty crazy, right?
This idol that was an idol 20 minutes ago, now that he's
shaved something off of it, it's מותר mutar, as well as the
shavings. Because but that's why I think it's not about how broken
it is. It's about the mindset of the non-Jew saying, look like
I don't even care about this anymore, I'm using it for scrap
metal, you know? Okay. לצרכה, l'tzarcha, if it's for the sake of
the idol, היא אסורה ושיפוחיה מותרין. hi asura v'shipuheiha mutarin. So this
is interesting, right? If he does it for the sake of the
idol, he's trying to like upkeep the idol,
right? The idol's still obviously אסור assur 'cause it's still an idol,
but the shavings themselves are actually
מותר. mutar, matter. So the
case is
that והישראל ששיפה עבודת כוכבים, V'HaYisrael she'shipah avodat kokhavim, בין לצורכו בין
לצורכה, bein l'tzorkho bein l'tzorkha, היא ושיפוייה אסורין. hee v'shipuhei asurin. So
but if a Jew comes along and does it, then everything's still
אסור, asur, right? So you're seeing the pattern here and you can
look at תוספות Tosafot to actually ask the question, like why do
we keep doing this? This answer's the same. Like what kind of
challenges are these when they're kind of the same challenge over and
over again and we know that the answer can be the same?
So אמאי, Amai? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. So ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, according to your opinion, תהא כעבודת כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה, tehey k'avodat
kokhavim she'nishtabrah me'eleha, it should be the same thing as an idol
that breaks on its own, right? This should be מותר mutar. also.
הכא נמי כדרבה. Hacha nami k'deRava. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish answers
the same thing. This also goes like the opinion of רבה. Rava.
Theoretically it would be מותר, Mutar. but we've made a גזירה gezeirah
to make it אסור asur so that Jews won't pick up the
idols.
איתיביה. Eitivei. Try again. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, שוחק וזורה
לרוח או מטיל לים. shokhek v'zoreh laruach o matil layam. But
we don't have that same concern by non-Jew, which is why if
it breaks on its own and it's still in the non-Jew's possession,
you've nothing to do with it, that's why it'd be okay.
Well, so the comparison is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying like
almost like a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, right? If it breaks on
its own and it's מותר, Mutar, like all more so if someone
comes along and smashes it, so who cares if that person's a
Jew, right? Right. So he's saying those, they both should be מותר.
mutar? No, trying to say like why ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would
say then, if he's so מחמיר machmir there, why is he מקל
meikel over here? So the answer is, yeah, that's a Jew, we're
worried about a Jew, we're not worried about the non-Jew. You're saying
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? No, no, it was ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan keeps on asking him these questions, and ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, it would seem that it should be okay, but
it's not. And then ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying it really
should be okay, really, but we want to be מחמיר machmir by
a Jew. But in the case of an idol that breaks on
its own, as long as it's in the non-Jew's possession, right, we're
not worried about the ישראל. Is that it? And why aren't we
worried about it
there? Right, that's, so that's, you're looking at the opinion of רבה,
Rava, right? ריש לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't really care about the, he's
using this to
like get out of the question from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But
yeah, רבה Rava's position is that, it's like we don't care about
the non-Jew picking it up, exactly. The גזירה gezeirah just applies to
the Jew because this special rule that we have that once a
Jew owns an idol,
it can't be מבטל. Right? Okay. Yeah. I'm kind of wondering how
much of what's behind that גזירה Gezeira is we don't want Jews
being vigilantes and going out there and stirring up the non-Jews by
smashing idols. By smashing their idols. That's interesting. I was thinking more
the opposite, like you know, we just don't want Jews just not
to like get involved with עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. You know what
I mean?
We're worried they're going to like you know, be נמשך אחריה. nimshakh
achareha. Right, but if they're going out there with the sledgehammer, I
don't think they're going in to worship. That's interesting. Yeah, well but
the גזירה that רבה Rava's opinion is, it doesn't, it doesn't mention
anything about therefore you shouldn't go smash, right? He's not doing it
in order that they shouldn't smash it. He's doing it in order
that they won't pick it up. But you're saying maybe there's an
underlying reason that it's so they won't pick it up in order
to smash it. Yeah, that's interesting. I was seeing it more kind
of like Michael did, like there's something more powerful
about a Jew who does עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right? Like that's
like in our קישקעס kishkes it just feels like ickier and so
we're saying like you can't just get out of that quickly by
מבטל-ing it, right? You can't go and do that kind of a
sin and then be like, oh I'm מבטל-ing it. But if they're
out there with the intent to
smash, that doesn't feel to me like engaging in any form of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Right, no but in that case smash, but
the other times we don't want people, oh it's very nice, looks
very pretty, you know? Look, I don't want to get too caught
up in it, but I think the counter to your point, right,
you know, is would be that you can go out and smash
it, just don't pick it up first. Right.
Like so so that to me seems more... but you could be
right. That's interesting. Yeah,
okay. Right,
so okay, איתיביה. Eitivei. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, שוחק וזורה
לרוח או מטיל לים. shokhek v'zoreh laruach o matil layam.
So when you find an idol, presumably רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is
saying you should grind it down and then throw it to the
wind or throw it into the sea, right? How can you throw
it into the sea if you don't pick it up? Right, so
so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi I also was wondering, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi's clearly not inside the opinion of רבה, Rava, right?
He's, he's more, this is like, you'll see the חכמים Chachamim like
you know, counter him. This is a discussion I think that must
exist outside of that גזירה because they're trying to figure out like
how do you get rid of idols, right? That's what I imagine.
אמרו לו אף היא נעשית זבל, Amru lo af hi ne'eset zevel,
right? So actually you're saying grind it up and then throw it
into the sea and then right you've totally destroyed it, it can't
do any benefit, it's totally gotten rid of. And
the rabbis are saying back to ר' יוסי, Rebbi Yose, well no,
what about those ashes, the dust that comes from the idol can
be used as fertilizer? It's going to end up if you throw
it into the sea or out onto the field, it's going to
end up being fertilizer.
וכתיב לא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם, Uk'tiv lo yidbak b'yadcha me'uma
min hacharem, right? So and we have
this פסוק Pasuk that says you shouldn't
even there shouldn't be anything left
from what's forbidden, from the nations of what's forbidden, right? Don't leave
any little thing left over is what they're trying to say, right?
So if these, so ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is saying to
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, if this little the dust from a ground
up idol still holds can
still hold the power of עבודה זרה Avoda zara and you wouldn't
want to be נהנה Ne'eneh from it, then like אמאי תהוי כעבודת
כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה? Amai tehavi k'avodat kochavim shenishtabra me'eleha?
So how does that fit with your opinion? It
should be at least as good as an idol that breaks on
its own.
הכא נמי כדרבא, Hacha nami k'deRava, so this is also goes like
רבא Rava and here's where we come in with your question David,
right? So oh no no no, רבא Rava actually comes in and
makes a גזירה on this also so you can't even pick it
up and grind it to dust and throw it into the wind.
So what's he supposed to do? In other words you find an
idol, right? So in some ways that's worse then, you can't, you
just have to keep it there? Right? What are you supposed to
do? You just ignore it? I don't know. Or maybe just you
could bury it. Or maybe, yeah, I don't
know, but you have to pick it up to bury it, right?
No, you could put, you dig a thing and kick it in
or something like that. Put dirt over it. Put dirt over it,
yeah. Yeah, it's not on a pedestal or something. I don't know,
it's a good question. Like what does this leave much, it doesn't
leave much,
we had just quoted this פסוק Pasuk that says get rid of
it all, right? How are you supposed to get rid of it
all if you can't
even do any of these things to get rid of it? So
interesting question. Okay, איתיבי ר' יוסי בר יאשיה אומר מצא צורת דרקון
וראשו חתוך. Etivei Rebbi Yose bar Yoshiya omer matzat tzurat drakon verosho
chituch.
So, you find a image of a, this is like a דרקון.
Drakon. רש"י Rashi says like דומה לנחש Domeh l'nachash I think, right?
Like it's some kind of, yeah, and you see that, they're like
dragon snake like things. Yeah, it's just funny who would have thought
there would be dragons in the גמרא. Gemara. I hadn't seen that
before, that's fun.
And it's set, it's the phonetically that it's the same, I like
too. Maybe it's discussed it says in the next, yeah, it'll come
back to דרקון Drakon what exactly it looks like. Yeah.
Okay, and its head is like cut off, right? Okay, so this
seems like a broken an idol that's been broken, right? ספק עובד
כוכבים חתכו ספק ישראל
חתכו. Safek oved kochavim chatacho, safek Yisrael chatacho. So we're not sure
if it was a, you just kind of find it, so we
don't know if a non-Jew broke it, like cut off its head,
or if a Jew cut off its head. מותר. mutar So when
we're not sure, we
say okay fine it's
מותר, mutar, we're going to assume that it's by
the we're going to let ourselves go be מיקל Meikel and assume
that it was the non-Jew that broke it. וודאי ישראל חתכו אסור.
V'vadai Yisrael chatacho assur.
If we know that a Jew broke it then it's אסור, Assur,
right? אמאי? ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says תהוי כעבודת כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה,
Tehavi k'avodat kochavim shenishtabra me'eleha, it should be the same thing as
what you say ריש לקיש Reish Lakish by one that breaks on
its own. הכא נמי כדרבא, Hacha nami k'deRava, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says, no this also goes like the opinion of רבא. Rava. Okay,
getting tired of this yet?
Okay well we're gonna change it up a little bit. איתיבי
ר'
יוסי אומר אף לא ירקות בימות הגשמים. Etivei Rebbi Yose omer af
lo yerakot biymot hageshamim. So we're gonna come in and talk about
a situation where there's an אשרה Ashera there's a tree
that's dedicated to עבודה זרה Avoda zara and we have this question
of whether you can like plant vegetables underneath it, right? And we
know from elsewhere we the this conversation is going around the idea
assumption that in the summer you can't obviously can't plant vegetables
or something else under an אשרה Ashera because the shade is going
to benefit the plant and what you planted and then you're going
to be getting benefit from this idol worship, right? But there is
no limit?
If they worship a mountain, you can never use the mountain? If
they worship a what? A mountain, then you can never use the
mountain or a river or anything. It's an interesting, so I know,
I know an אשרה Ashera like the a tree that's it's a
specific category. So it's a good question how far does this go,
right? Do they get to like lay claim to your
apartment? Good question. I'm not sure. I would imagine there's a limit
as to what we can. I don't know. It's a good question.
But a tree we're saying we know particularly that can hold kind
of this status just as much as an idol can or something
else.
So sorry, so in the summer months we know for sure you
can't plant anything underneath it because the shade is going to benefit
what you plant and then you're getting benefit from this אשרה, Asherah,
right? But we have a question of maybe בימות הגשמים Be'imot Hageshamim
maybe in the rainy months, right, in the winter, you could plant
something under it because in that case Rashi tells us, right, the
צל, tzal, the shade is actually going to be bad for the
plants, right? Like you don't your plants don't need more shade in
the winter, it's actually going to harm them, so maybe you could
plant under it because they're not getting any benefit from the tree,
right? So but this Rabbi Yose is saying you can't do that
מפני שהנביאנה נושרת עליה, mipnei shehaniviana nosheret aleiha, right, nosheret
aleiha,
so because the foliage, the leaves are going to fall off and
fall onto the what you planted and that's going to benefit them,
it's going to turn into like fertilizer and benefit them. So אמר
amar, says Rabbi Yochanan תהא כעבודת כוכבים שנשתברה מאליה, tehe ke'avodat kochavim
shenishtavra me'aleha,
so those leaves that fell off, it should have the same status
as like an idol that broke on its own, right? They've kind
of broken off the tree of their own accord, right? And so
why wouldn't that Resh Lakish have the same status and be מותר?
mutar,
So Resh Lakish answers שאני התם דעבודת כוכבים קיימת, Shani hatam de'avodat
kochavim kayamet, right?
So that's different because that the tree isn't affected, right? The tree
is still standing and whole and the kind of the עיקר ikar
of the עבודה זרה avoda zara is still just as good as
it was before.
So so that's different than an idol that breaks on its own
and where the idol's actually broken and no longer you know functional
or no longer the same as it was. Okay. והא, but here
we're going to have a question on this, והא שפיים דעיקר עבודת
כוכבים קיימת, veha shipuyin de'ikar avodat kochavim kayamet, but we remember our
example from before about the shavings that were shaved off, right? And
we said that it was that it was מותר mutar. then, right?
If it was shaved off for you
know for something other than the sake of the idol, right? We
said it was מותר, mutar. right? And in that case the idol's
still standing also, right? Like the main part of it's still standing,
right? וקתני לצורכה, Vektani letsorkha, right? לצורכה, Letsorkha, sorry, וקתני לצורכה היא
אסורה ושפיים מותרין, vektani letsorkha hi asura veshipuyin mutarin, right?
And we said that if it was done for the sake of
the idol that the the idol is אסור asur but that the
shavings are not. So it seems like the shavings and the leaves
should have the same status, right?
So the response is Rav Huna בריה דרב יהושע bere deRav Yehoshua
אמר, לפי שאין עבודת כוכבים בטלה דרך גדילתה. lefi she'ein avodat kochavim
betela derech gedilata.
So actually
idols or you know sources of עבודה זרה avoda zara can't be
מבטל דרך גדילה derech gedila like in the course of like the
normal way that they grow or that they yeah that they grow
or mature or whatever. So this tree, it's normal for the leaves
to fall off, so it can't be מבטל based on that kind
of normal occurrence, natural occurrence. Okay, so at least we didn't answer
it with Rava's opinion, right? Okay.
איתיבי, Eitivei, so Rabbi Yochanan's going to try again, right?
Resh Lakish is doing a very good job of you know keeping
his opinion alive. איתיבי, Eitivei Rabbi Shimon... oh no, sorry. Now Resh
Lakish. Thank you. We're done. Resh Lakish has tired out Rabbi Yochanan.
Now it's Resh Lakish's turn to challenge Rabbi Yochanan. Okay,
so איתיבי Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish to Rabbi Yochanan, קן שבראש האילן
ken sheberosh ha'ilan של הקדש, shel hekdesh, לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo
nehenin velo moalin.
So we have the case of there's a tree,
first just okay just imagine a tree, nest on top of it,
right? Okay, so there's two trees that we're going to be talking
about. The first one we just said is a tree that's been
dedicated to הקדש, hekdesh, right?
And what we say is that you can't benefit from it, לא
נהנין, lo nehenin, right? Because there's a nest in the tree and
we know that you can't benefit from things that have been made
הקדש, hekdesh, they need to be saved for the temple.
ולא נהנין, Velo nehenin, I mean sorry, ולא מועלין, velo moalin, right?
So you can't benefit from it, but we also say that if
בדיעבד bedieved you do benefit from it, you haven't done מעילה, me'ila,
you haven't like misappropriated it. So we so we're reading into this
that דרבנן derabbanan it's not allowed, but דאורייתא de'oraitta it is, right?
It's דאורייתא de'oraitta it's not actually a misuse of הקדש hekdesh if
you take that nest off of the tree because otherwise. They also
say that if בדיעבד *bedieved* you do benefit from it, you haven't
done מעילה Me'ilah *me'ila*, you haven't like misappropriated it. So we know,
so we're reading into this that דרבנן *de'rabbanan* it's not allowed, but
דאורייתא *de'oraita* it is, right? It's דאורייתא *de'oraita* it's not actually a
misuse of הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* if you take that nest off of
the tree because otherwise we would say that you've misappropriated it even
if you do it, even if it's already been done. בראש של
אשירה Asherah, *berosh shel asheira*, so the second case that we're going
to be looking at is a nest on the top of an
אשירה *asheira* tree, right? יתיז בקנה *yitiz bekaneh*. Is אשירה *asheira* generic
or is it a specific species of tree? Oh that's a good
question. I should have done my research on אשירות *asheiras*. I'm not
an expert. I was imagining it as just a tree that's been
designated to עבודה זרה avodah zarah? *avoda zara*, but you might be
right. Does Artscroll tell us anything? I would imagine Koren would tell
us, give us a picture even.
I'll look it up at the end and that's a good question.
I should know the answer. I'm not sure. But it says in
the Bible אשירה כל עץ *asheira kol etz*. Sorry?
It says in the Bible אשירה כל עץ *asheira kol etz*. So
maybe it's generic. So yeah, I don't know.
Okay, so all right, so the first case it's at the top
of a הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* tree. The second case the nest is
at the top of an אשירה *asheira* tree and we say you
can knock it out, יתיז בקנה *yitiz bekana*, you can knock out
the nest and get the nest. So that would seem like you
can benefit from it, right? So ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* is saying,
so this, this,
hold on, I'll finish his opinion, he keeps going. קא סלקא דעתך
כגון ששיברא ממנו עצים וקינתה בהן וקתני יתיז בקנה *kasalka d'atach kegon
sheshibra mimenu etzim vikinta bahen vekatani yitiz
bekana*, right? So what makes sense if you see a nest at
the top of a tree, right, you would think the bird has
taken twigs from the tree and made the nest,
right? And so therefore the nest is like definitely like you would
think it would be part of the tree. It's made from the
same twigs as the tree, right? And so by saying יתיז בקנה
*yitiz bekana*, by saying you can knock it off and use it,
right, it seems to be saying that it seems to line up
with ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*'s opinion of an idol that breaks on
its own, right? So this the ecosystem of the tree has broken
off these twigs on its own, right? The bird has come along
and broken them off, the twigs have been broken off and now
they're a separate thing and it seems like you can benefit from
them, right? So that seems to line up with ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish*'s idea that an idol that breaks on its own would be
מותר mutar *muttar*, right? So that's his challenge to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*. והכא במאי עסקינן *vehacha b'mai askinan*, so what are we talking
about here? Here's רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*'s answer, כגון דאייתי עצים מעלמא
וקינתה בהן *kegon de'aytei etzim me'alma vikinta bahen*. So actually no, no,
no, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, wrong assumption. The bird didn't take the
twigs from the tree that's הקדש Hekdesh. *hekdesh* or that's אשירה *asheira*,
right? He took it from a different different tree and then he
brought it to that tree. So therefore it's not like an idol
that broke of its own accord
and it doesn't support your opinion. And he's going to explain further,
דיקא נמי דקתני גבי הקדש Hekdesh לא נהנין ולא מועלין *dika nami
dikatani gabi hekdesh lo nehenin velo mo'alin*. אי אמרת בשלמא דאייתי עצים
מעלמא היינו דקתני גבי הקדש Hekdesh, לא נהנין ולא מועלין *ei amart
bishlama de'aytei etzim me'alma haynu dikatani gabi hekdesh lo nehenin velo mo'alin*,
sorry, hold on, I'm getting ahead. Okay, so the language of the
משנה Mishna. *mishnah* is specific in this, right? By הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh*
it says you can't be נהנין *nehenin* and but בדיעבד *bedieved* there's
no מעילה me'ilah *me'ila*, right? And if you're saying that it's from
and it this works according to what I'm saying that it's just
twigs from some other tree from the world that this has been
brought to the brought to this tree that's הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* or
that's
אשירה *asheira*, right? Because so it makes sense that it would be
like that because by הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* it says you can't benefit
from it and but בדיעבד *bedieved* it doesn't do it's not מעילה
*me'ila*. So the לא נהנין *lo nehenin* מדרבנן *m'derabbanan*, right? So דרבנן
*derabbanan* we say that you can't benefit from it, ולא מועלין *velo
mo'alin* מדאורייתא *m'de'oraita*. דאורייתא *de'oraita* we're saying it doesn't actually count, right?
דהא לא קדישי *deha lo kiddushe* because it's
not doesn't hold the weight of הקדש Hekdesh, *hekdesh* like the tree
does, right? אלא אי אמרת *ela ei amarta*, but by you know
what you're trying to say, ששיברא עצים ממנו וקינתה בהן *sheshibra etzim
mimenu vikinta bahen*, that the bird took the twigs from the tree
itself and built and built the nest from it, אמאי לא מועלין
*amai lo mo'alin*, right? Wouldn't that that doesn't make any sense, wouldn't
that be מעילה *me'ila*, right? Wouldn't that be misuse of
הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh*? What would how would it make sense that דאורייתא
*de'oraita* we would... מעילה *me'ila*, להועיל *leho'il* is to benefit, right, so
it could be either one. So
מעילה *me'ila* it's a specific category where we're saying you've taken something
that's been designated to
Yeah, it's a particular category, right? So we're
saying we know דרבנן you're not allowed to benefit from it, but
it doesn't actually technically fall into the category of מעילה that's something
that's actually been misused.
Okay. So Rabbi Yochanan asks Resh Lakish, like, it makes sense according
to my opinion that it's from a different, twigs from a different
place, but according to your opinion,
that it's twigs from that thing, how can you say that that
wouldn't be misuse of הקדש Hekdesh if he's taking, if you're getting
benefit from a nest that's made of twigs from a הקדש tree?
Right?
How we doing?
Yeah? Okay. הקדשי, Hekdeshei, right, it should be הקדש. מידי איריא Midi
irya Resh Lakish says, but that's your proof? Come on. You can
do better than that, he says. הכא בגידולין הבאין לאחר מכאן עסקינן.
Hacha begidulin haba'in l'achar mikan askinan.
So we're talking about the twigs that grew, the bird took twigs
from the הקדש tree to build his nest, yes, but they're twigs
that grew after the tree became הקדש, right? Someone made it הקדש
and then the tree grew more twigs, right, trees keep growing, and
those are the twigs that the bird used.
וקסבר אין מעילה בגידולין V'kasvar ein me'ilah begidulin and so, sorry, אין
מעילה בגידולין. ein me'ilah begidulin. And we know that when you make
something הקדש and then it continues to grow that there's no מעילה
with that. Interesting question, I would be curious to look up more.
What about if it has fruit then? Is the fruit not prohibited?
Right, it's... not just that, you make a cow הקדש and it
grows, it's not like only the part of the cow... But if
you have a tree in your field that's הקדש, you can't bring
it to the... you don't cut it down and bring it to
the... well you're going to be selling it and using the money
I would
assume to bring to the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But it's a weird thing, אין מעילה בגידולין.
ein me'ilah begidulin. Like,
I mean we talk about people's making animals הקדש all the time
which grow, and you're right, fruit from the tree, I mean it's
weird, I don't... I'm not sure. I didn't look into it more
but I'd be curious to look at the הלכה Halacha and see
what's going on.
Okay. We are going to, okay, so Resh Lakish has kind of
bolstered his challenge to Rabbi Yochanan, right? He said, no no no,
it's from that tree and it breaks, the bird breaks it off
and you can still use it, so my challenge to you holds,
that should still be like my idea of idols that break on
their
own, and if that's מותר, mutar the idols that break on their
own should also be
מותר. mutar ורבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן V'Rabbi Abahu amar Rabbi Yochanan
so now we're going to quote Rabbi Yochanan as you know defending
himself, right?
אמאי יתיז, Amai yatiz, what is it that you're knocking off, right?
יתיז באפרוחין. Yatiz be'afruchin. So you're actually, you're knocking out the little
baby birds that are in the nest, not the actual nest itself,
right? You're, so you're not benefiting, Rabbi Yochanan says in this example
that you're bringing Resh Lakish, you're not benefiting from the twigs from
the tree that's הקדש or that's אשירה, you're actually just getting the
chicks out of the nest, right? אמר ליה רבי יעקב לרבי ירמיה
בר תחליפא Amar lei Rabbi Yaakov l'Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Tachlifa אסברא לך
באפרוחין כאן וכאן מותרין בביצים כאן וכאן אסורין. asvara lach be'afruchin kan
v'kan mutarin bebeitzin kan v'kan asurin. So then we further this a
little bit and we say,
and just to clarify, if you take the chicks, if you take
the baby birds out, you can benefit from them,
but בביצים bebeitzin but if it's the eggs, you can't benefit from
them, right? So the eggs are considered part of the nest in
some kind of integral way and therefore and you actually can't benefit
from those, so that would seem a good defense of Rabbi Yochanan
of why it would be
אסור assur for the idols that break on their own as well,
right? Because these even these eggs that are part integral part of
the nest are אסור. assur. אמר רב אשי ובאפרוחין שצריכין לאימן כביצים
דמו. Amar Rav Ashi v'ba'afruchin shetzerichin l'iman k'beitzin damu. So just another
little added point
that and in fact little baby birds that are so young that
they're still dependent on their mother are also,
they're like eggs and they're also אסור, assur, you can't benefit from
them.
Okay wait I need a drink of water.
Is this yours? Yeah that one, the blue one, thanks. Okay
we're going to try, we're going to start the next
משנה. mishna ל' דף Lamed Daf but we'll see if we
can get Rabbi Elazar off to at least towards the beginning of
the next דף daf for tomorrow. Okay, המוציא כלים, Hamotzi keilim, the
משנה. mishna The משנה mishna, says, someone who finds vessels of some
sort, ועליהם צורת חמה, צורת לבנה, צורת דרקון. va-aleihem tzorat chama, tzorat
levana, tzorat drakon. And on the vessels that you find are, is
an image of a sun, or the image of the moon, or
the image of this dragon character that we met on the last
עמוד. יוליכים לים המלח, yolchim l'yam hamelach, יוליכים לים המלח, yolchim l'yam
hamelach, you should go and you should throw them into the ים
המלח yam hamelach to the Dead Sea. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer,
שעל המכובדין אסורין. she'al hamchubadin asurin. If they’re on, these images are
on vessels that are מכובדין, mchubadin, that
are important looking
or nice, particularly nice looking vessels, then they’re אסור. asur. שעל המבוזין
מותרין, she'al hamvuzin mutarin, but if they’re on like dingy, the גמרא
gemara is going to discuss further what exactly this מכובדין המבוזין mchubadin
hamvuzin is.
Expensive, מכובדין mchubadin may be expensive, yeah it’s unclear, but if they’re
on like disgraceful, dirty, whatever, like שפחי shpachi vessels, then they’re מותר.
mutar. Interesting, not what we’re going to deal with in this דף,
daf, but an interesting point.
Okay, so the גמרא gemara comes in and says למימרא דהני
הוא דפלחי
להו למדי אחרינא לא. l'meimra d'hanei hu d'palchi lehu l'midya achrina lo.
So is this משנה coming to teach us that these three things,
the sun, the moon, and the dragon, these three images are things
that עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim worship,
but other things they don’t? Right? That seems weird. מנהו, minhu, so
let me I’m going to challenge
you with another ברייתא baraita or another, let’s see where it’s from,
yeah from
חולין. Chullin. השוחט לשום ימים, לשום נהרות, לשום מדבר, לשום חמה, לשום
לבנה, לשום כוכבים. hashochet l'shum yamim, l'shum neharot, l'shum midbar, l'shum chama,
l'shum levana, l'shum kochavim. So if you slaughter something for the sake
of the sea or of the river or of the
desert or the sun or the moon or the stars,
לשום כוכבים ומזלות, l'shum kochavim umazalot, or like the constellations, לשום מיכאל
שר הגדול, l'shum Michael sar hagadol, for the sake of Michael the
like ministering angel, לשום שלשול קטן, l'shum shilshul katan, or even for
the sake of the smallest little worm, הרי אלו זבחי מתים. harei
elu zivchei meitim. These are,
it’s like a slaughter for the dead, it’s like for idol worship,
right?
And it’s אסור. asur. אמר אביי,
מפלחי
לכל דמשכחי פלחי. miflach l'chol d'meshkach palthi.
So what they worship is anything that they find, right? Anything they
find they’ll worship it. מצרי ומפלחי, mtzari u'mfalthi, but something that they’ll
like actually create and make in order to worship, הני תלתא. hanei
tlata. It’s those three things, the sun, the moon, and the dragon.
דחשיבי צרי להו ופלחי להו, d'chashivi tzari lehu u'palthi lehu, because it’s
the creation of
it is important and then they worship
it. Okay. למדי אחרינא לנוי בעלמא עבדי להו. l'midya achrina l'noi b'alma
avdei lehu. So or you know maybe they, they make it just
like
for adornment, right? So if they make it, it’s those three things,
and
other things that they make it’s like to adorn, to like make
things nicer, but not actually in order to worship it seems.
Okay, so we’re going to dig in more to this idea of
like distinguishing between things that are made and things that
are found. And those are going to be treated, there’s going to
be like a different set of things that are אסור asur if
they’re found versus if they’re found. but not actually in order to
worship, it seems. Okay. So we're going to dig in more to
this idea of, like, distinguishing between things that are made and things
that are found. And that those are going to be treated, there's
going to be, like, a different set of things that are אסור
assur if they're found versus if they're made.
Okay. So
מנקט רב ששת menakit Rav Sheshet so מנקט רב ששת חומרי מתניתא
ותני. menakit Rav Sheshet chumrei matnita v'tani. So Rav Sheshet went around
and like compiled all of the rules, all of the חומרות, chumrot,
and taught them all together, right? He made it easier for us,
he brought it all into
one ברייתא braita and says this. כל המזלות מותרין חוץ ממזל חמה
ולבנה. kol hamazalot mutarin chutz mimazal chama u'levana. So all of the
like celestial bodies, right, are מותר mutar except for... מותר mutar for
what? מותר mutar. like the images of them or... to use them.
Right. Just like... so we're going to discuss if it's if you
find it or if you make it or what, but you have
a thing with an image
of anything other than the sun or the moon it's מותר. Because
it says specifically
in שופטים, Shoftim, השמש והירח. hashemesh ve'hayareyach.
So maybe that's why the focus on the sun and the moon.
Okay. וכל הפרצופין
מותרין ve'chol hapartzufin mutarin and all faces are מותר חוץ מפרצוף אדם
chutz mi'partzuf adam except for the face of a person, right? So
we'll look at more what that means. וכל הצורות מותרות חוץ מצורת
דרקון ve'chol hatzurot mutarot chutz mi'tzurat drakon and any image or shape
or you know image I think it's meaning here is מותר except
for that of the דרקון. drakon. Okay. What kind of celestial bodies
would they have known of except the sun and the moon?
Stars, constellations, yeah they're big into like, you know, Mars, I don't
know, right? Which actually is weird you would think for sure Mars
would be אסור, assur, right? Amie says Mercury. I don't know, right?
Because we know Mars is like
the god of whatever. But anyway, but yeah that's what it means.
Anything other than the sun and the moon.
Okay. אמר מר, amar mar, so
רב ששת Rav Sheshet said, כל המזלות מותרין חוץ ממזל חמה ולבנה
kol hamazalot mutarin chutz mimazal chama u'levana so you're saying it's everything's
fine except for the sun and the moon. הכא במאי עסקינן אילימא
בעושה אי בעושה כל המזלות מי שרי? hacha be'mai askinan i'leima be'osei
i'be'osei kol hamazalot misharei? So if you're saying רב ששת Rav Sheshet
that anything's fine except the sun and the moon, like what in
what situation are you talking? If you're talking about making the idols,
you're saying I can go out and make, create an image of
like you know Mars and it's not אסור? assur? Like why would
that be allowed?
והכתיב, ve'ha ketiv, and we have this פסוק, pasuk, לא תעשון אתי
אלהי כסף ואלהי זהב לא תעשו לכם. lo ta'asun iti elohei chesef
ve'elohei zahav lo ta'asu lachem. Right? Don't make any kind of idols
to go with me, right? With me God, right? There shouldn't be
any idols of anything else, right? So we know you're not allowed
to make other idols and the interpretation that they're going to use
here is לא תעשוני כדמות שמשי המשמשים לפני במרום. lo ta'asuni k'demut
shimshai hamishmishin lefanai bamarom. Don't make any images of
like my attendants up in the heavens, the other powers that are
up in the heavens with me, right? Which seems to be any
other kind of constellation or stars or planets or whatever else, right,
would seem to fall into that category and this פסוק pasuk says
you can't make those. So can't be that you're saying you can
make images of anything of any constellations other than or any celestial
bodies other than the sun and the moon.
אלא פשיטא במוצא, ella pshita bimotzei, actually but it's obvious that it's
talking about when you find them. You're finding an image something that's
already made with an image of something that's not the sun and
the moon and that's מותר. וכדתנן המוצא כלים ועליהם צורת חמה צורת
לבנה צורת דרקון, uk'detanan hamotzei keilim ve'aleihem tzurat chama tzurat levana tzurat
drakon, so it's quoting our משנה, right? If you find it and
it has the image of the sun or the moon or the
דרקון, drakon, יוליכים לים המלח. yolichim l'yam hamelach. Those you have to
throw into ים המלח Yam Hamelach and presumably other things you don't,
right? I don't think it means literally just an expression to throw
it into the sea. Probably you could throw it into another body
of water also. Just throw it in the garbage. Hold on, I
want to just... concerned that those objects you found were used for
worship or something? Right. So we're trying to parse out what we
have to be worried about and what we don't, right? Because I
mean at what point are you not going to be able to
go back to the question you asked earlier at what point are
you not going to be able to use anything, right? Like that
mug has some like interesting patterns on it, right? Like how do
I know that wasn't used for עבודה זרה? But I mean just
in terms of the quote from you know שמות Shemot about servants
at you know up high, so those would be things like the
stars, right? Right, but that's an idol, right? So we're saying you're
finding a jug and it just has some patterns on it, right?
If you found an idol that was like the stars or an
idol of Mars, like, yeah, okay,
you can't use an idol. But this is just like a thing
that has a picture on
it. Okay. איבעית אימא מצי *Iba'is eima matzi* well maybe we
should maybe this is actually a good place to stop because we
have to get pretty far down in order to finish this סוגיא
*sugya*. So we'll stop here about six or seven lines up from
the bottom of מב עמוד ב *Mem Beis Amud Beis* and Rabbi
Linzer will pick up with this again tomorrow. We're going to look
at tomorrow the we're going to break down רב ששת *Rav Sheshet's*
statement, the three parts of it, right, about the constellations, about
the faces,
and about the דרקון *drakon* and look at each of those three
pieces separately and try to figure out how to make them all
be either finding or making.
And we'll pick up with that tomorrow. Thank you. But this עבודה
זרה *avoda zara* strictly deals with idol worship, but there's no reference
to anything Christian.